Let's move now to the disk structure. How
is the physical disk organized in order to
maintain one or more filesystems? So before
we start with this,
think about the following question:
You have your laptop and it's currently turned
off. You know you have the disk. What is persisted
on the disk is there and you can of course
read it and write it. And now you know that
you actually read and write in blocks.
And then you have your main memory, but that
is volatile memory, so since the computer
is turned off for what we know, it's empty.
Now you know that you turn the computer on
and magically your operating system starts
and then you can run your processes and so on.
So the question is:
How do we do that? so we know that we will
need to read for sure something from the disk
and bring it into memory so that we start
the processes and the very first process that will
start is the one that will
actually eventually lead to the operating
system
being the process that runs, like we saw this
when we discussed processes with the init
process. But how is this actually physically
done? Well, the answer to that is that
again, this is collaboration between the hardware
and the operating system. There is an agreement
about how things are stored on the disk
so that when you turn on the computer, the
hardware
can go and take from the disk things and start
the operating system. Because as we just said,
when the computer is off, volatile memory /
main memory is basically empty, so where is
the operating system? How does the operating
system know what to do given that it does
not exist yet? So this starts based on how
your disk is organized. There is a fixed structure
for the disk and the hardware is aware of that
and it uses such knowledge to actually boot
your computer.
So this is how it looks. You have partitions
and each partition is basically a file system
Inside each partition we will see you have
the initial part that is about the specific type
of file system and the rest that is actually
dependent on what the users are doing with
that file system.
But we also have something called the master
boot record and the agreement between the hardware
and the operating system, and in this case
also the disk is that
this exists at the very beginning of the disk.
OK, it starts at sector 0. If you have a rotating
disk or at another address, but there is an
agreement about where it starts. Let's say
it starts at 0 in this case, and what you
put there is the minimal
set of instructions that the hardware knows
it needs to read, put in memory and start executing,
and that set of instructions are going to
be the ones that decide which file system
to load, so inside which partition to go,
and based on that which files to load to actually
start the operating system
The partition table, so the information about
all the partitions is found at the end of the
master
boot record and again it's used by the code
that you store in the master boot record to
actually decide which partition to run. So
if you have a computer and you have multiple
operating systems, it means that you have multiple
most likely partitions on each partition as
a different file system, and what you put
in the master boot record is a set of instructions
that will interact with the user asking the
user which system do you want to start, and
based on that, decide into which file system
to go and which things to load to actually
wake up the operating system.
This again, it's done in a similar way, so
basically at the very beginning of each partition
you have the boot block. There you will put
again the stuff that the hardware needs to
load into memory and start executing to actually
start the operating system, so that is
where you will put the operating system. Maybe
not all of it, but at least the minimum set
of instructions you need to wake the operating
system up and then let the operating system
go on with the rest of tasks.
This is what I said before. After the boot
block usually have this so called Super Block
which contains information that is needed
by the operating system. But now it's specific
to the operating system you are trying to
load and to the file system that you use to
maintain the information of the operating
system and after that you will have extra
things, but these usually depend on what
the user is storing on the
file system, the files, what space is free,
which again of course is a function of what
the user is doing with the file system, and
so on and so forth.